so to continue that suitor
we spoke about last time we only got to
the third perception that needs to be developed
developed
this is the fourth one it says when
ambiku becomes accustomed
to the perception of non-delight in
regard to the whole world
their mind draws back from the various
beautiful things in the world
and either equanimity or
the other side gets established
yeah so we said in the big the first one
was the beautiful side of the ugly the
the beautiful side of the ugly the
living side of
death and necessary the necessity of
food the necessity
right right have you ever found it food
is dennis
you subjected to it and dependent on it
there's no choice about it
yeah soon except it's a burden
so this is saying
the perception of non-delight well it's
it's to to
uproot the inherent delight
joy in regard to the world in regards to
the senses
in regard to the sense objects
by developing what well by developing
the non-delight
and you're developing on the light by
seeing the danger of the light
so for example seeing things you delight
in like everybody
in the delight the translation the word
the light is not
it's not like you're you're over the
moon ecstatic
and delighted it's it's it refers to
that uh
subtle attitude of acceptance of looking
forward to
on a mental level towards things that
are pleasing and agreeable
so you delight you're related on that
mental level there is joy
at the prospect of something pleasant
and that so things that are pleasant are not
that so things that are pleasant are not
problem in themselves but it's you
being unable to not delight in the
prospect of pleasure that's where the
problem is
because uh delighting in it means not
seeing the inherent danger
if you're seeing the inherent danger in
things you're delighting
towards you'll stop delighting
you're not going to blame those things
or like
try to try to never see anything
agreeable or hear anything agreeable
ever again
it's just that you will not delight in
it so if it's agreeable it's known as
agreeable but there's no delight
if it's disagreeable it's known as
disagreeable there is no no
there's no like resistance to it which
is the opposite of their delight
so abs not delight refers to the absence
of the light that doesn't refer to
hating that which you delight him yes
it's no longer attracted to the beautiful
no longer attracted to the beautiful
things in the world yeah
you are not attractive that doesn't mean
the beautiful things in the world cease
to exist
it's the same means you've done delight
in it and you can't just
um fabricate non-delight out of thin air
okay now just practice non-delight you
can only practice non-delight
by preventing yourself from delighting
it and the only way you can prevent
yourself from delighting it is by
contemplating maintaining the context of
the danger
in things that you are delighting in
so you cultivate non-delight then and
you do that long enough then
you don't have to constantly keep
reminding yourself of the danger because
the danger is inherent in those things
that's why
freedom from those things is possible in
the first place
but it's not seeing the danger you build
up the delight so to speak in the course
of lifetime
well lifetimes
you get taken by the like with food you
get taken with the tastes
exactly and the taste is the yeah the
taste is the measure the taste is your
motive that's where your motivation is
rooted and and yeah the food is a good example
and and yeah the food is a good example
because here you can you can abandon
things that are non-essential
like agreeable sight sounds smell taste
touches you restrain from and you can say no to
you restrain from and you can say no to
all of it because you know the light in
them is bad
okay but that still doesn't mean
you you understood the light simply by
saying no to these things
because there are certain things you
can't say no to such as eating
and yes even the buddha himself tried to
stab himself to death to see if that would be
himself to death to see if that would be
the way out of
complete freedom of the mind and he saw
actually it isn't
it was being done for the wrong reasons
the food was never the problem
so things that you can't just say no to
such as food
that's where you have to then practice
developing of that context of
of danger in delighting in it not
the food i'm eating is dangerous but my
delight is the day my delight is that which
is the day my delight is that which
keeps me bound
to this aimless wanderings of samsara
and foreign the danger of delight
the danger of the light not the danger
of food the danger of delight in food
and then if there is no delight in it
then yeah you wouldn't care what you're
eating good or bad and that's what would have
good or bad and that's what would have
said himself and that's what i think
when that man praised him and he said
what do you see word in me
of praise did you on the count of what
are you praising me basically
and he said oh a master gautam is one
who eats little praises eating little
and he has disciples that he little and
then he missed all these ascetic
practices and he said that's absolutely
not true i have i have disciples
true i have i have disciples
that sometimes don't eat for two or
three days and yet
sometimes i would eat kings and queens
would serve me
like the the most refined food you can
imagine manage with their own hands
and i would eat a bowl full to the brim
sometimes two bowls fall to the brim
two bowls fall to the brim
if they were to respect me on a kind of
eating little they wouldn't because i
don't always be a little
and then he debunks every ascetic
practice in itself as word of respect
and he says no why they respect me
because i've shown in the path out of
suffering i showed them and then all
these ways of practicing the dhamma
that they understood for themselves so
they know important is important
and non-important is not important like
blaming the food and so on it's not
important your delight is important you understand
your delight is important you understand
the way out of delight
you wouldn't care if the person who
taught you the way out of the light is
eating six bowls of food
because you understood what you mean and
even if that person say
you learned it from somebody say you
learned it from sodapana
the way out of suffering and you're
practicing it
and you see it in them that they are not
necessarily practicing it
they are eating carelessly even that you
wouldn't haul against them so to speak
it's just yeah it's whatever they do
it's on them
so whatever they do it does not
invalidate the truth of the dhamma the
truth of the instruction that that
person has understood obviously the buddha
has understood obviously the buddha
himself did not eat
all this food out of carelessness he ate
because he was necessary to eat because
he was hungry
the hunger was determined how much he'll
eat he didn't seek out kings and queens
to serve in food and rejecting lower no
he just happened to be in such
environment such circumstances
but the point is that if you judge a
book by its cover
you will you you will put the cover
first and and the message of the book
second but it should be other way around even
but it should be other way around even
if the cover of the book deteriorates
and doesn't necessarily uphold the
greatest standard of ascetic practice
is the message basically impenetrable
to to criticism the message of freedom
from suffering is the principle behind
freedom from suffering
absolutely true universally yes you
understood it yes
doesn't matter if the whole book gets
destroyed doesn't matter what what the
person who told you that
do or or like in later in their life and
so on
what matters is that the message you got
are that's the truth that's what matters
so you measure your practice not by how
much you can go without food and how
harsh you live and so on
you measure it how um
how much more you're free from that
delight how clearer you understood the nature of
how clearer you understood the nature of
the light and how
more apparent perception of danger and
their delight is
and we would explain that to this man
it's like oh yeah yeah that is what's
word of respect
okay you can easily find things to like
or dislike on the on the base of a cover
and sometimes unfortunately people would
dismiss the message
of a person the teaching because they
don't approve of the cover
oh it's not the right color and so on
obviously this man wasn't that shallow
but he was still equating practice with
certain just
uh austere kind of protocols he says
that's why his response was not at all
oh yeah and then the other one was like
somebody wears silk robes
like you know the silk robes made by
bowling bugs to death
so they produce the silk always the
buddha did not ask for it but somebody
gave him the silk robes and he accepted
it
i mean from the ascetic point of view
that is
absolutely outrageous not just that he
wears this comfortable silk rose but
also silk was made by killing animals
yeah and the buddha did not say it's an
offense you mustn't wear it he said you
mustn't ask for it to be killed but if
somebody does it and give it to you it's
fine and then he said he has monks that wear
and then he said he has monks that wear
like absolute most roughest
basically barbed wire type of hemp ropes
and if that's the level of what should
be respected they will completely not
respect him
so it's basically knowing the heartwood
as the woulda would say
from the external appearance of the word
knowing what's the essence
yeah and that's the essence when it
comes to any sensual restraint
you do it first of course out of faith
and out of that kind of creating a
buffer zone
but in itself things you're restraining
against were never the problem their
secondary problem
they're a symptom of your problem
symptom of your delight
because that's the thing you are
directly responsible for
you know when you have a central thought
appearing in your mind
you did not create it in itself now you
can choose to entertain it and prolong
it and revolve around it
that's on you and all that comes out of
delight that's what the buddha would say
among dedicated to mindfulness and and
practice when when a sensual thought arises
when when a sensual thought arises
he doesn't enlighten it he doesn't
welcome it he doesn't entertain it
and this the similarly we we talked
about it before if somebody comes at
your door
and wants to get in obviously and now
you feel pressured and you open the door
either go and chase them or let them in
and so on
no the point is to recognize no they
can't get in unless i let them in
but if i go out well that's another way
of engaging with it so
they win if i let them in that's another
way of engaging so they win again
so can i endure the pressure at the
doorstep without letting it in
without basically losing my control and
going out and sharpening them or
something so that's that's that's how and that's
so that's that's that's how and that's
how they will leave
that's how you get rid of it you don't
get rid of it by feeding it by engaging
with it by acknowledging it
you get rid of it by not acting out of
it and you will not act out of it
if you don't delight in it so delight is
a necessary basis
for acting towards sensuality you cannot
possibly act towards sensuality unless
you're delighting in it
and you cannot possibly delight in it
unless you lost or never had
the sight of danger in that what you're
delighting in
to cultivate non-delight you will
literally experience this passion
towards the entire world it doesn't
matter up down left right past future beautiful
up down left right past future beautiful
ugly
um godly humanly whatever
there is no delight in anything that
appears for you
unless you're peaceful yeah absolute
absolute peace
and uh perception number five says when
a bhikkhu becomes accustomed
to the perception of a nietzsche their
mind draws back from acquisitions
honors and fame and either
equanimity gets established or the other
side no it gets established
so yeah the other side the counterpart
of
acquisition ownership failure
is a true understanding of that
non-ownership impossibility to own as we
often say
when it comes to nature see thief things
are and each other we said before i won't
and each other we said before i won't
get into it again but um
just to kind of mention again
it is not the impermanence that you can
observe like look i destroy this
thus it's impermanent destruction
of a thing is another thing that has
arisen for you
so it's only a relative destruction
you're not destroying your experience as
a whole you're experiencing
this is present and now it's all chopped
up
that doesn't mean that this is
impermanent just means it has changed
and it's ah so change so nature is
change
but saying everything is changing it's
not personal enough
you want to see that yeah everything is
changing but also
me i am my experience the whole
my ownership my body my senses my
feelings my life
oh so that is also subject to change
so that's what i'm saying is not about
seeing the impermanence because you
can't see the impermanence of your life
unless you're dead but then you can't
see it
so if you wait for death to show you
that your life is subject to change well
it's too late
and that's the whole point saying that
something is subject to change
means the possibility of change is
inherent in it without that thing
changing so understanding that things are subject
so understanding that things are subject
to change subject to suffering means
understanding that
before change change will have to be
inevitable so you don't wait for it to change you
so you don't wait for it to change you
want understanding while it's not
changing while your life is there
you won't understand that it's overall
fundamentally going to change and the the nature of
going to change and the the nature of
change is that nature of
uh non-mastery non-ownership
impossibility to control
so you can control things within their
rising while they're present so you have
a say in your life
now but fundamentally you will not have
a say
when that life decides to change as in
you die
so it's like seeing the fundamental
basis of your
basically acquisitions get escalates
into honors escalating to fame
escalates into that whole kind of
extension yeah yeah exactly extension himself
yeah yeah exactly extension himself
that's where the buddha when he was
talking about those different layers of
conceit that the monk who practices
would would move like firstly would be the
would move like firstly would be the
course sensuality and anger and
but then later on in the practice he
would be removing the thoughts
of uh of basically his nationality
as in on that general level of what you
are where you were
of a greater scale more subtler
like of his clan of his family of his
country or whatever even if you were not
or whatever even if you were not
necessarily the great
national patriot or something in your
original life or whatever
you nevertheless you still identified
with the culture the environment you
lived through
and those are subtle subtler
acquisitions but yes
acquisitions honors and fame so fame is
inherently accepted and liked by people
lack of fame is inherently feared by
people that are people irrationally feel
fear blame
even if there is no rational basis for a
criticism just to fight these criticism
at you
you're already defending and against it
and don't want it
it takes a developed mind to not do that
to see
through it though the worldly winds and
all of that comes from simple
appropriation of the very things that
are in front of you
you're very experienced you're very very
fine aggregates the feelings the
intentions you already acquire them as
yours but if you contemplate that not this is
but if you contemplate that not this is
impermanent that's impermanent
my experience as a whole in the utmost
sort of
general background of i am sitting here
talking to you while the dog is messing
around we are recording
all of that fundamentally is because my
body with the senses is here
operating and i cannot do anything about
that and that subject to change
as we said in other talks if your heart
will just stop
none of this my control within it
would be this also taken so i can
control i can move
i can say yes i can say no i can look
this way but all of that is within the
non-control all that is within the basis that i have
all that is within the basis that i have
no access to i'm not privy to the basis
of my aggregates
so when they change my entire domain my
entire world
life of control will be swept away with
it and you can recognize that
through like your experience right now
that is in your control
you can recognize that fundamentally
this is all subjected
to change that's it you have to wait for
it to change you don't need to make a
change to prove yourself it's subject to
change you just need to stop acting out of it
you just need to stop acting out of it
unwholesomely and descended whether you
want it or not
subject of change is implicit it defines
the thing pretty much
hence the understanding of of a niche
and then there is then even if oh this
is mine emotionally there is no
acquiring of that because emotionally
you're already approved but you approve
to your emotions by seeing that they're
subject to change
so how can you then possibly be
emotional kind of something secondary to
it
you can't take things personally anymore
but because you have you won't go
further yeah that
perception of nature won't take you
further into taking basically exactly
and it will start undoing if you make if
you cultivate that perception furniture
sustain it maintain it in its being
literally uh it would result in
completely fading away
of all the acquisitions which would
result in any way of all that like
honors depending on honors notions of
conceit the greatness the clan
the belonging the sense of self in the
greatest sense so you will be completely
free of the slightest traces of conceit
like you're saying the other day and
that i think is that's what going
forth is isn't it that's the going forth
is the actual
establishment it's the establishing of
the yeah that's the real well like basically
yeah that's the real well like basically
establishing of of that
my life is subject to nietzsche in a
more kind of acute manner
see when you live in your home your
family your routine
with your with your village with your
province in your country
all of these are like layers and layers
and layers of acquisition
familiarity familiarity exactly exactly
and why is familiarity
valued because he doesn't change not as
often at least
not my family his expedition exactly
exactly so why do
then oh my family change well but at
least we are still the clan we still
have a family name
oh but at least we are this way at least
we're in this country and so on we like
so you have this greater and greater
identity why because it doesn't change
as much as the other one
and why do you don't like change well
because it reminds you of the very
very core of your being you are not your
own and that's something that people
and that's something that people
throughout their entire existence tries
to outrun
try to cover up and keep the lid on it
that's so that's that's the norm
but then if someone wants to go forth
exactly you have to remove these
false safety zones that you created you
will not understand it immediately well
some did as soon as they went forward
they became our hands so that's the
meaning of going forward so you know
what is to start emulating what you need to
is to start emulating what you need to
abandon before it's too late
so that's what i mean like today often
you have people just go
into their into the monastery but it's
not really that they left the home
they just replaced one more like a
smaller setup of a family and
familiarity with the biggest setup of a
bigger family and familiarity
i.e tradition oh this is the way and
this is the way and everyone must
and there's no thinking for yourself
because if something for yourself you
realize oh well all of this is second tradition
oh well all of this is second tradition
family name
uh i'm such and such monk this is
what all of that is secondary what is
first is that you choose to be there
for the reasons of safety but like why
do i need safety
what are you protecting oh you're
protecting sense of ownership you're
protecting yourself from anxiety you're
protecting your feelings you're
protecting from uncertainty because you might
from uncertainty because you might
overwhelm your mind so you realize that
today you can have
somebody gone forth for decades and
still basically a layman mentally you just
basically a layman mentally you just
kind of
extended the setup of a home into a
bigger area
so yes it's not as it's not as as
narrowed as like a little familiarity of
my little nuke in my house
so you do kind of expand a little bit
but overall
you haven't really you haven't really
abandoned everything all of these uh
buffer zones that your own conceit needs
to protect its own ownership and send
itself if you're good you're born into the
if you're good you're born into the
buddhist tradition oh yeah yeah yeah yes
i'm talking i'm not even talking about
that but no that's even more that's more
like well let's just
become part of it you never leave the
society by being a priest
because you're just part of the social
structure what please do for whom
that's your career you've never left
home yes too i'm not talking about that
i'm talking for people who do want to
practice and kind of go forth but then
you realize
but now you just replaced one
familiarity with another familiarity
and now you're afraid to leave this
second familiarity even to the point of
remember you've seen it many times people are
you've seen it many times people are
afraid to change the monastery just
for a period of time or even um or let
alone change the monastery that's in a
different tradition
and that's just like whoa but wait you
are homeless
so why would this be such a big deal
well like certain places why i can't go
there because you know
the routine is too different there or
there is no routine that's the worst
fear people would have
when they come what's your there is no
routine you're on your own
so nobody there's no structure no
traditional authority demanding from you
what to do throughout the day and that
is the most frightening thing
if you're basically not honest with
yourself fundamentally and realize that
that's where the practice is
well that's what the going forth is
that's what the guardian for literally
there is
and that's what they said it's once you
do it rightly in the suttas
nothing can match that level of freedom
like like a
mountain deer like anything lower than
that would be
feeling like a trap in prison yeah dusty
the home life is dusty yeah
the home life is crowded and dusty many
people frequented
constant hustle and bustling but
now even the monastic life is crowded in
dust yes it can be yeah you just go from one
yes it can be yeah you just go from one
fifth
you make and it happened even in the in
the suttas where they were reprimanded
when they were and they weren't even
like you know they were all probably
areas at least or maybe even someone in
varanasi don't matter when the buddha
came it's like what's this
noise and racket here
and then how will we sewing robes and
organizing cloth
all for a very good purpose and he told
him off for being in a crowd
of monks not like outside the lay people
or something
so you could say like okay so if that's
not acceptable
how much more that's true for like just
you know being fully engaged
physically in the crowd society and
people and so on
yeah you need to do something give some
teaching one way or the other but
to what extent that compromises the
lifestyle of solitude
if you're a monk that's gone from home
from family life
to another temple temple life well i
think more crowded than your home
beforehand because yeah i mean that's quite common
because yeah i mean that's quite common
but then you have to
go forth you still have to go forth yeah
so
yeah that that monk who's stuck in that
familiar tradition
of buddhist monasticism needs to
actually go far from that need can he
go far from that need can he
stop being a monk but still actually
without yeah without this problem without the
yeah without this problem without the
throat yeah
no that's that's the thing like
your practice should be defined by like
as i said it starts of course by sense
restraint virtue learning the rules but if you
virtue learning the rules but if you
never
upgrade it from that level you are still
defined by these random observances
that's why literally virtue
and my duty is the very first fatter
that sought upon abandons
and that's exactly what it is he leaves
it without
breaking it but not holding it anymore
not quite not holding it as an
acquisition so to speak
because you really are it's about the
non-delight it's about non-greed
non-aversion on delusion
did you get an account of sense
restraint if you made the right effort so then you
if you made the right effort so then you
can literally be a monk anywhere
in any circumstance because it's not
about what you do
not even like what you wear so to speak
it's just like an external statement for
others it's about what you're incapable of
it's about what you're incapable of
thinking why you're incapable of
pursuing internally
anything based on great diversion
delusion
so non-delight brings dispassion change
seeing that you yourself in its core of
your very being
are subject to change that's enough to
approach your sense of ownership
and then in what you see this is just
what you see and what you hear that's
just what you hear
it's not like more or less want don't
want and say oh this is agreeable this is
and say oh this is agreeable this is
disagreeable this is comfortable this is
uncomfortable none of it is is besetting
or overwhelming my mind
and it's uh it says your mind draws back
from fame or reputation really
fame or reputation really
from yeah exactly distribute so yeah oh
those people
my family might think that um
what other people will think about you
yeah yeah that will that ceases to be
your your concern
yeah no
you will not lose perspective on it on
account of that irrational fear of blame
or and the pressure to make sure that
they have the right view of you no that's
have the right view of you no that's
gone as well you know that's rooted in
your conceit
so if people might again you're trying
to control that which is uncontrollable
other people's opinions literally but
okay many people can understand that but one
many people can understand that but one
thing is to understand that on a
rational level
and another thing is to let that
rational level settle in so you're
emotionally unpatheted in regard to blame and
unpatheted in regard to blame and
criticism
even emotionally cannot be touched let
them mentally
revolve around it and that's why you
will be unable to lose perspective so if
somebody criticizes you
you would be absolutely clear about
where they're coming from and you could
see actually they have a point i was
actually they have a point i was
completely wrong in that regard and you
wouldn't have a problem admitting it
either because you're not irrationally
because you're not irrationally
defending your conceit your
your your criteria's ownership and
equally if they're criticizing you realize
if they're criticizing you realize
that's absolutely ridiculous that's even
not true
completely misses the point but you
wouldn't feel pressure to
i must correct and rectify the world and
and make sure that everybody knows the
truth defend you
your honor defend your honor defend your
name
so reputation like again
it's it's like like sense restraint
initially you want to practice sense
restraint and you want to keep the
veneer rules
and you don't want to break that
reputation as you don't want to break the nurture
as you don't want to break the nurture
but if you never
upgrade from that level you still remain
dependent on circumstances
which means if circumstances then
criticize you even if you haven't
actually did anything to break your reputation
did anything to break your reputation
just somebody doesn't like you or they
disapprove of you in any other way and
then they just find things to blame you
for you'll be affected by it because you
you'll be affected by it because you
stayed on that level with these things
where these things are subjected to that
you're depending on the circumstances
not criticizing you not blaming you
yeah you're your equanimity is dependent
on that
and that's that's not the economic
that's a very limited equanimity
shaky ground very shaky ground yeah
because literally
so my my well-being
depends on the opinion of others like i
can't even
i don't have a saying how my own
thoughts arise
i only have a saying whether i delight
in them or not
and here i am assuming i should have a
say in how other people's thoughts arise
and what they think of me
no all i can do is no delight in it not
try to reject it to resist it
irrationally saying what you do to yourself that's
saying what you do to yourself that's
why that he knows it internally he knows
it externally
it's the same thing same attitude in
regard to both
or internally and externally
so yeah then you you're kind of
bulletproof for whatever happens
externally yeah you you basically left
that short
where these things are happening you're
not there anymore
there's nothing for you nothing nothing
it's impossible for anything to land on
you yeah
because you're simply not dead you don't
have to psychologize or
no the reasons that other people are
saying these things yeah and that's
another thing you know
like when people sometimes say that um
like i don't somebody offends you
and you're really angry and you can't
you still bear the grudge and then you
find out that that
person was abused as a child
and now you're not angry with them no
that's just psychologizing you never
approve of the anger
you just basically updated the
circumstances and now this is acceptable for you to
and now this is acceptable for you to
not be angry
you don't want to be angry in the first
place regardless regardless of person
who offended you
was sort of abused and went through lots
of suffering or didn't you don't
be offended by full stop because offense
is on you it's not on what's being said
but if you need to justify the source of
the offense says ah see i forgive him
because such and such
oh you still blame what's being said for
offense you're not taking responsibility
for it
on the emotional level which means
sooner or later that will have to change
so sooner or later you'll be back to
suffer again on account of some some
other offense
because what stops you to find out that
actually no they were not abused as a
child and they were not a victim
and then you can find out again whatever
they were then you can find the word
so you're fully thrown dependent on the
worldly winds
praise blame faint and you just ah left
right trying to avoid one failing to see that
trying to avoid one failing to see that
the other one will have to come because
of it
so seeing that the problem is not in the
world in the movement of the world
it's in your own delight non-delight
resistance or craving against it
you stop doing that it doesn't matter
you don't have to manage the world
anymore and that's the true freedom no you're
and that's the true freedom no you're
not burdened by action
the things you have to do otherwise
you'll drown in your own suffering
and the continuation of this suitor
seven angus 7 49
this is perception number six when obiku
becomes accustomed
to the perception of dukkha in
nietzsche an acute perception
of fear or danger becomes settled in him
towards indolence laziness slackness
heedlessness lack of effort
and unreflectiveness just as one would
have fear
towards one's executioner with a drawn
out sword
oh time is short actually yeah so yeah
the niche becomes established so yeah
niche becomes established so yeah
because that's where like regardless of
what you do what you think
you remain subject to change which means
at any time it can occur
in an unfavorable manner so once you
recognize the weight of that
the gravity of that situation oh that's
that's uncomfortable that's the duka in
that change
the the the inherent unpleasantness in
that not being your own not being in your own
not being your own not being in your own
control not having a say over your own
life fundamentally
it depends upon external random things
such as functioning organs that you have
no say in whatsoever
so you recognize that anita correctly
you will be
recognizing the discomfort of that
situation and the clearer it is the more
of the sense of urgency will develop
because i know i remain even if i choose
to ignore it or rest go to sleep or
whatever else not think about it
i remain subject to it so you can see
like everything is at stake at any given
time so you can see you look am i being lazy
so you can see you look am i being lazy
am i sitting back really and enjoying
things well that's the thing and that's
you would also understand what true
laziness is
sitting back and relaxing is not
necessarily laziness
mentally as we discussed in that talk
delusion delusion
that's what laziness is mentally given
into oblivion
turning away distracting yourself
ignoring that you are you can just spend the
that you are you can just spend the
whole day laying on in a bed if you want
but not for a second should you allow
your mind to forget about
the perilous situation that is in
undermined by change that's not in your
control and you'll be practicing contemplation
and you'll be practicing contemplation
and meditation regardless of your body
posture but you also you can't entertain the
but you also you can't entertain the
idea that you've understood
anitra dukkha unless you're feeling that
urgency yeah and there's no urgency yeah that
yeah and there's no urgency yeah that
hasn't been developed well you're either
in arahant
because there's no urgency you're fully
free so there's nothing divergent about
or you you don't even understand with
any change
but it's a clear sign there can be a
clear red flag for you
if you practice a nature correctly that
discomfort of dukkha
will be apparent you cannot practice the
nietzsche and not
but laziness can be a sign of that
danger you're in
that you haven't understood yeah yeah
yeah the fact that you can still
turn and engage in laziness yeah well
that's what was said even like uh
sort of if you were to see them he would
be sort of trying to revoke
the sense of urgency in them he said why
well because there is still work to be
done and if you see another he wouldn't try
and if you see another he wouldn't try
to invoke sense of urgency in it
yeah because there is nothing to be done
anymore so that's literally to be done
so that's literally to be done
work to be done not like experiences
that might happen to me if i'm lucky no
literally you and your effort is the sole
you and your effort is the sole
determination
if you sustain the effort and do it and
do it and do it the results will have to
follow if there are no results it's either
if there are no results it's either
because you're not doing enough effort
or your effort is
misplaced as in you're doing wrong
things putting effort in wrong things
you're hoping things will just work out
exactly i'm just doing this but do you
recognize what you're doing as a
practice his work
do you recognize that as pertaining to
freedom from suffering freedom from
delight inability to suffer amidst the worldly
inability to suffer amidst the worldly
winds is
do you recognize that for fact do you
see a relationship between the two or
it's more like yeah yeah my life's
getting better but i don't quite see the
connection i'm just doing this
because you know it makes me feel good
means you don't really know what the
work is
or does it so how can you then do the
work if you don't know what the actual
work is
hey can you build me something i don't
build me a table
you don't have a clue how to build a
table how can possibly build a table so
first you need to understand what the
work of building a table is
to produce a table
so the work of of non-delight the work
of penetrating through and understanding
the nature of things
the work of knowing where the problem is
oh the problem is nothing that
somebody's in front of my door
the problem is that i can't help being
affected by it either open the door
try to change them or open it or let
them in either way
so if you just think oh i must change
them so you're making all this effort to
sense restraint sensory strain
completely wrongly on the wrong basis
you don't understand what the problem is
but when you see that danger you're
surrounded by it means you already
did a fair amount of work to because
the injury is not seen because the
entire life the ethanol existence is
about as i said out running it and covering it
as i said out running it and covering it
up keeping it at arm's length
so if you manage to see the danger
either circumstances forced it upon you
but then again many people experience
the danger and the peril and fear for
their life and so on but they don't get
wisdom and i can't do it because the
moment the circumstances have changed
they're back into their old ways
some people however don't even need to
experience the circumstances at all or
you just recognize that they are
subjected to all of this
and that in itself is all the danger you
need all the recognition all the recognition
all the recognition all the recognition
you need yeah
because that recognition as well of
being completely surrounded or
you know the execution of sword is on
your neck you're tied up
at any point he's going to do it
yeah that could freak people you know
yeah well they freed them out because
again they don't know what the problem
is
like you would think the problem is you
think you can avoid the sword you can't
he will cut your head off
but people don't realize that so they
still act out of this notion that
they're in control of their life
so they just have to be extra careful
and don't
make a wrong move so the executioner
will cut the head off no it's not about
making a wrong move
that's why people call that suta to
justify this ridiculous
sensation watching practice of moving
moving sittings i must not let the second slip
sittings i must not let the second slip
because they're chopped my head no your
head's being chopped anyway
so the only thing you can really do that
will make a difference there it's not
not make a wrong move because it makes
no difference he's there to cut your
head off
he's basically abandon that which will
be destroyed
when he drops his sword where
and that can be next second in 10 years
doesn't matter the sword is there i see
it
do i still hold on to the ball do you
still holding my emotion am i still
attached to my life am i still
delighting essentially
abandon that before the sword comes not
okay touching touching moving moving
sitting sitting laying laying second one
two three four you're wasting your time
that's not a problem you can't save this
body from being chopped
by the executioner you can abandon it
before it's chopped
and you don't abandon it by focusing on
it you're abandoning it by removing the
ownership that underlines it
it's underneath it
but you don't remove the executioner
it's inconceivable so that whole the
famous suit of
you would be as careful like not to
spill not to spill the
the water because you'll cut the head
off that's a different suit but
you would be as careful in the sense of
ah i will not give in to delight
even to the point of spilling slightly
towards it because then
i'll i'm subjected to being killed
not like i will freeze and spend the
rest of my life in this catatonic stupor
of meditation
without making a slightest motion
because no you have to recognize that that
no you have to recognize that that
assassin in that other certainly
compares who lives in like your best
friend inside you that's you basically
your own assassin because you remain
even under death
and that's inside you cannot outrun that
you cannot escape that
so you can only like escape in a sense
of ah get rid of it or something
so you can only abandon that which he's
about to assassinate
and you abandon it by seeing what's
subjected to it what is what is subject
to oh it's just
subjected to execution this body is
subject to the
to the assassin that is his goal
so i have a choice either ignore that
try make the most of it
or abandon that which will be killed
remove my ownership of it through seeing
the inherent danger and actually
impossibility to own because if i'm true
owner if i'm truly in control of this life in
if i'm truly in control of this life in
this body no assassin can come and kill
me
but the fact that i am subject to death
means i'm
subject to fun my control is
fundamentally subjected to non-control
so there's really no choice about it in
other words so i'm like oh yeah but i
don't mind the execution
no you do because you value life you
value ownership
and this is completely opposite of that
to be taking away ripping it away from
you so the only thing the only reason you
so the only thing the only reason you
think you don't mind is because you're
so intoxicated with your ownership you
you don't even acknowledge the threat
of a drawn sword ah but no you can't get
me
and then catch but then it's too late
for you to do anything about it
but if you see that the reason you don't
become afraid and well you will probably
be afraid initially because you don't
really know where the problem is and
what can i do what can i not do
but the clearer you are about the
practice the less and less afraid you
are because you realize well this is
inevitable and and also it's not about me trying to
and and also it's not about me trying to
control the uncontrollable
like body movement never move and no
only a little bit and
no it's about not delighting when i
delight so just remove the light remove greeter
so just remove the light remove greeter
aversion
distraction that's it you have closed
the gates through which assassin
and the executioner can come and kill
you
and oh that's the true safety and that's
that other suit that uh
the monk was going on the photos saying
oh this is so blissful you're so
blissful and people thought oh he must be
and people thought oh he must be
thinking about his previous former wives
or whatever
because he's so like he's not happy with
the monk's life then
they called they told the buddha they
would have called him up he says what
are you referring to when you say so
blissful is it your previous lay life is
like what no
no no no it's the other opposite he said
when i
was a layman he was a prince constantly
in fear of his life by his own family by
other kings whatever
because he was next in line of thrones
so so he never had a moment of peace
wherever he was he had to get guards
with him
his palaces were guarded inside and
outside constantly he was constantly
living in fear that he'll be killed
and said and now after practice dharma
and obviously fulfilled it
i'm living in this utter complete
wilderness of a jungle with tigers and
elephants it's like
deadly things my life is much more at
risk now
than it used to be yet i feel complete
ease and peace
and not traces of fear and that so he
remembers the previous life
he sees that disparity how worse how
much worse off he was before
and it's just delightful for him to
remember like how how long
he has come so that's the thing like
with all the protection in the world
no because the reason for you being
subjected to fear and danger is
internally because you delight in things
that are subjected to fear and danger
not because there is fear and danger
right yes and no protection needed no
yes and no protection needed no
protection neither because there's
nothing that was like whenever you like when we
that was like whenever you like when we
said in the previous uh recording
leading up to this oh you you you never
like dare to leave the monastery or home
dare to leave the monastery or home
whichever way because of the safety but
if there is
a need for safety means you're
protecting something
and if you're protecting something means
you have taken up the ownership of that
which means there's dhamma missing there
and there's definitely pressure there's
partition
you're subject to that
so then the last perception
when ibiku becomes accustomed to the
perception of
anata in what is dukkha
his mind is devoid of eye making mind
making and conceit
regarding this conscious body and all
external objects
it it has overcome all measurements
due to conceiving yeah and that's that's
exactly what i'm saying
measurement is due to conceiving is that
to the extent you conceived
to that measure you're subject to losing
needing to protect it safety fear
to the extent you developed your
ownership to that extent you'll need to
defend it
to that measure you are subject to all
the things that
what you've appropriated is subjected to
change discomfort and so on so you remove
discomfort and so on so you remove
your conceivings there's nothing it can
be measured by
and that's that's why seeing a nietzsche
correctly subject to change his experience felt
subject to change his experience felt
unpleasantly
which is then lived as not mine
not myself as an artist
because the necessary basis for arta for
sense of ownership
and i am i am the first everything else
is second
for me is not seeing
that that i am is subject to change
which is uncomfortable which is not mine
so you are not yours puttujan is not his
arahant he's not his but
thinks he is while he is not his that's
what he is liable to suffering and
everything else because he
lives the discrepancy of it aran doesn't
think he is
he's not his and that's why you're able
to free yourself from ownership because
your ownership
was just a misconception from the start
you've never really owned things
obviously that is the start it's we said
the ignorance is beginningless there's
not a point where you made a mistake and
became the owner
so ownership is the beginning list it
shouldn't be there you cannot own things
but not knowing that that's how you own
things and that not
knowledge of ownership is beginningless
that's some side and that's a video
but that's why once you understand that
ownership is impossible
you cannot revert back to ownership
nothing can happen that can
revert you back from another hunt
into or even from assault upon into
petunia it's irreversible
because you're discerning what's there
basically on account of which you used
to mistake the ownership
so now the mistake is uprooted and you
cannot possibly
engage with it anymore you can't
knowingly you can wisdom
develop ignomance it's mutually exclusive
so developing that perception yeah
totally perception or not
of an art and with a set not
not not me not mine
not i am that's the contemplation that
sort of
should be cultivating whatever he
experiences
present past future feeling perception
no matter not me not for
me not i am not mine basically
reminding himself of what he understood
ah not mine
reminds me of the impossibility of that
thing to be on in the first place
yeah just you just keep contemplating
another correctly
re-reveals anichenduka yeah yeah
just contemplating uh anichi correctly
you will feel dukkha your experience in
atta automatically simultaneously
so one two three you can emphasize one
two three but the others are there with
it
anichinduka and anatomy
those three things are recognized
stronger that perception gets
yeah you need to just basically
fortifying efforts what to find those
very things the same things
yeah that fortification of those
perception is the work that needs to be
done cleaning yeah polishing polishing but if
cleaning yeah polishing polishing but if
you use that similarly
polishing and polishing and polishing
and polishing and polishing
you